Guide to the Daniel W. Jordan papers, 1827-1935 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
Daniel W. Jordan papers 1827-1935 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Jordan, Daniel W., 1810-1883.
6.5 Linear Feet Approx. 4563 Items
Planter and legislator of Camden, South Carolina.
Collection comprises Daniel W. Jordan family and business correspondence, account books (1836-1877) and other financial papers, Jordan's accounting diploma from 1827, shipping records, notes on family history, and other material. Includes records and correspondence concerning Jordan's turpentine business, plantation management, the sale of cotton, slavery and associated labor and production, the University of Alabama at Tuscaloosa, St. Mary's College (Raleigh, N.C.), the wreck of the steamship Charmer (1861), in which Jordan's daughter perished, and student life in Charleston, S.C.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48-hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Daniel W. Jordan papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library in 1934, with additions in 1997 and 2004.
Collection Overview
Family and business correspondence and accounts of Daniel W. Jordan, planter and owner of Laurel Hill plantation, slaveholder, and South Carolina legislator. The many pieces of correspondence contain references to the University of Alabama, Tuscaloosa, 1847; letters from Benjamin Blossom & Son and De Rossit & Brown, both of New York City, concerning Jordan's turpentine business; correspondence concerning slavery; letters from W. J. Gingham of W. J. Gingham & Sons' Select School, Oaks, Orange County, North Carolina, concerning Valentine Jordan's attendance, 1860-1861; letters from daughters "Sallie Vic" (Victoria Jordan), 1857-1858, and from Cora Jordan, 1860, while they attended a school in Charleston, South Carolina; letters referring to the deaths of Victoria (Jordan) Davie and her husband in the burning of the steamship Charmer, 1861; and correspondence concerning Jordan's cotton business and relations with Lyon Brothers & Company of Baltimore, Maryland. Also among the correspondents are Joseph B. Bryan, H. G. Carrison, John S. Cheek, H. S. Ellenwood, William R. Harris, M; W. Ransom, John C. Tuttle and William A. Tuttle.
The plantation account books cover the period 1836-1877 and include lists of slaves, ration accounts, and cotton cultivation accounts. Also includes Jordan's bookkeeping diploma, 1827. There are receipts from Albert Smedes, St. Mary's College, Raleigh, North Carolina, for tuition of Rowena Ralston, 1854, and Victoria Jordan, 1856.
Addition (97-189) (4 items; dated 1866-1895 and n.d.) contains Jordan's personal and family reminiscences, most of which were written in 1868, accounts of Laurel Hill Plantation, possibly including slave accounts, chiefly in 1866 but also 1895, one letter, and apparent notes towards a will, undated. There is also a photocopy of reminiscences and family history.
Unprocessed addition (04-301)(300 items, 0.6 lin. ft.; dated 1834-1859) contains family correspondence, including letters to and from members of Jordan's extended family.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Jordan, Daniel W., 1810-1883
Jordan family
Charmer (Ship)
St. Mary's College (Raleigh, N.C.) -- Students
University of Alabama -- Students
College students -- Southern States
Cotton growing -- South Carolina
Cotton trade -- South Carolina
Planters -- South Carolina
Plantations -- South Carolina
Plantations -- South Carolina -- History
Plantations -- Economic aspects
Slaves -- South Carolina
Slavery -- South Carolina
Turpentine -- Economic aspects
Universities and colleges -- Southern States
Women -- Education -- Southern States
Charleston (S.C.) -- Description and travel
South Carolina -- History -- 1775-1865
South Carolina -- Economic conditions -- 19th century
Portions of this collection are also available on microfilm. Please consult with a Rubenstein Library reference archivist.
Contents of Collection
- Daniel Jordan papers, 1827-1935 and undated, (11 boxes and 1 volume)
  - Family correspondence, 1834-1863 and undated (Box 1)
  - Correspondence and accounts, 1830-1848 June (Box 2)
  - Correspondence and accounts, 1848 July-1851 June (Box 3)
  - Correspondence and accounts, 1851 July-1853 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence and accounts, 1854 January-1855 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence and accounts, 1855 May-1857 December (Box 6)
  - Correspondence and accounts, 1858 January-1860 April (Box 7)
  - Correspondence and accounts, 1860 September-1871 June (Box 8)
  - Correspondence and accounts, 1871 July-1935 (Box 9)
  - Other papers, 1827-1913 (Box 10)
  - N.Y. shipping and commercial lists, 1850 February-1851 July (Box 11)
  - Correspondence from N.Y., 1854 January-1854 July (Gilwood) (Box 11)
  - Manuscript volume: "List of Negroes," Camden, S.C., 1862 May (Volume L:2087)